Public Television Service
公 視 製 作
has produced the first documentary
台 灣 電 視 史 上
of Taiwan's history,
第 一 部 影 像 台 灣 史
starting from the birth of the island to the
從 台 灣 島 的 誕 生
end of the 20th century.
一 直 到 二 十 世 紀 結 束
Each episode of the documentary
節 目 中 的 每 一 段 故 事
is based on factual historical events.
都 真 正 在 歷 史 中 發 生 過
Each character is
每 一 個 出 現 的 人 物
a real person.
都 實 際 存 在 遇
Their dialogs are
而 他 們 所 說 的 話
based on historical records.
也 都 出 自 於 歷 史 文 獻 的 記 載
The ancestors of the indigenous and Han people
原 住 民 與 漢 人 的 祖 先
crossed the ocean at different times
在 不 同 時 期 橫 越 海 洋
to arrive at this beautiful island.
來 到 這 座 美 麗 島 上
For hundreds of years, the ancestors endured many wars,
數 百 年 來 祖 先 經 歷 了 無 數 戰 火
colonizers, and natural disasters.
殖 民 統 治 與 天 災
Yet the people of Taiwan persisted.
但 是 台 灣 人 民 堅 強 的 生 存 下 來
From being poor to being wealthy,
從 貧 窮 到 富 裕
from authoritarian rule to democracy,
從 專 制 到 民 主
the people of Taiwan strive to write their own history.
台 灣 人 民 共 同 打 拆 出 自 己 的 歷 史
This is our ancestors' attestation,
這 是 我 們 祖 先 的 證 言
one filled with trials, tribulations, and hope.
一 個 充 滿 磨 難 與 希 望
This is our story.
屬 於 我 們 自 己 的 故 事
Taiwan — A People's History
﹁ 打 拆 ﹣ 台 灣 人 民 的 歷 史 」
will share with the people of Taiwan
將 與 台 灣 人 民 分 享
the road taken by our ancestors and us.
祠 先 與 我 們 共 同 走 過 的 路
This is the first time in Taiwan
懋 該 是 我 們 台 灣 有 史 以 來
where history is systematically
第 一 次 真 正 系 統 性 的 透 過 電 影
presented to the general
或 者 說 透 過 電 視 ， 影 像 的 歷 史
public through television.
和 一 般 的 國 民 的 一 個 接 觸
The general public and the viewers
而 我 們 一 般 人 以 及 觀 眾
can simply watch the documentary.
可 以 透 遇 箍 影
They don't have to read books
不 用 再 讀 書
and scour through the pages.
看 到 眼 花 撻 亂
From the documentary,
透 遇 電 遇 電 影
viewers can reflect on what has happened
大 家 可 以 再 用 心 來 想 說
in Taiwan over the last few hundred years.
台 灣 這 幾 百 年 來 發 生 什 麼 事 情
We have written history of Taiwan,
為 什 麼 我 們 有 文 字 的 台 灣 史
and comic books that depict Taiwan history,
有 漫 畫 的 台 灣 史
yet there aren't any good films on Taiwan's history?
但 是 沒 有 一 個 好 的 影 像 台 灣 史
For that matter,
甚 至 不 要 講 好
there just aren't any films on Taiwan's history.
甚 至 連 個 影 像 台 灣 史 大 概 都 沒 有
We have all read The Indomitable Rose
那 我 們 都 讀 過 這 個 楊 逵 的
by Yang Kuei.
壓 不 居 的 玫 瑰 花
In reality, the society of Taiwan,
其 實 真 的 台 灣 的 社 會
the island,
台 灣 這 塊 土 地
is as beautiful as the rose.
就 像 玫 瑰 花 這 樣 地 燦 爛
We should know our history, and face our past.
我 們 懺 該 是 攤 開 墩 史 來 面 對 它
I believe that only a people brave enough
我 認 為 只 有 一 個 敢 於
to face history will have a future.
面 對 歷 史 的 民 族 才 有 未 來
Since it is the history of the people of Taiwan,
既 然 是 台 灣 人 民 的 歷 史
the entire history
全 史
therefore, must start from the creation of the world;
當 然 從 盤 古 開 天
it must start from prehistory.
從 史 前 史 開 始
This will make the history complete.
一 方 這 樣 比 較 完 整
At the same time,
另 一 方 面 這 部 分
this has not been done yet.
從 來 沒 有 人 碰 觸 遇
This documentary is the first and the most complete one.
這 是 第 一 部 完 整 台 灣 歷 史 的 影 片
We decided to film the documentary
我 們 就 比 較 大 膦 的 就 決 定
using reenactments and reconstructed scenes.
就 在 這 次 我 們 以 重 演 重 建 的 方 式
Unlike others, we will not use narration,
也 不 會 是 過 去 用 旁 白
interviews, photographs, and pictures
然 後 用 草 問 用 照 片 用 圖 片 之 類
to show history in a monotonous way.
比 較 死 板 的 方 式 去 呈 現 歷 史
This part is solemn and stirring.
看 到 這 段 多 憎 壯
For PTS,
射 次 八 世 雷 2 對 於 公 共 電 視 來 講
it accepts donations from the government
我 想 公 共 電 視 接 受 國 家 的 捐 贈
and the public.
然 後 援 受 人 民 的 捐 贈
If we could
那 廖 如 果 我 們 能 藉 由
film the documentary
一 種 比 較 具 有 活 潑 生 動 的
in a livelier and more touching manner,
紀 錄 影 片 方 式 來 加 以 處 理 的 話
we can enable more viewers to understand
其 實 可 以 讓 更 多 人 來 了 解
the past, present,
自 己 生 長 這 塊 土 地 的 過 去
and future of the land we live in.
以 及 現 在 甚 至 可 以 看 到 未 來
Viewers will want to watch
觀 眾 會 想 要 看 的
and will be moved by
以 及 真 正 會 感 動 的
the short stories in the documentary.
遼 是 這 些 小 故 事
Who did what?
誰 做 了 什 麼 事
Which events were triumphs of humanity?
那 個 事 情 是 人 性 的 光 輝
Which events benefited humanity?
是 對 人 性 是 有 幫 助 的
These stories are real; they existed,
我 覺 得 那 個 東 西 是 真 的 是 有
and can best reach out to the viewers.
有 跟 觀 眾 是 最 大 的 接 觸
Reading history
讀 歷 史 的 遇 程
is more of a rational process.
是 比 較 屬 於 理 性 的 過 程
But when I was filming the documentary,
可 是 當 我 要 拍 的 時 候
history needed to be slowly digested and ruminated.
這 些 東 西 慢 慢 消 化 到 反 芻
History is definitely about perception.
它 絕 對 是 愛 性 層 面 的 東 西
I think PTS must have accomplished something,
我 想 公 視 應 該 做 了 件 很 大 的 事 情
something important and good.
很 好 的 事 情
During the Japanese occupation,
大 致 是 在 日 治 時 代
there was an official,
當 時 有 一 個 醫 生 出 身 的
Goto Shimpei, who was also a doctor.
民 政 長 官 叫 後 藤 新 平
He wanted to correct
那 廖 他 認 為 他 要 改 正
some of the hygienic habits of the local people.
台 灣 人 的 一 些 衛 生 習 慣
So he came up with an
所 以 他 就 打 出 這 樣 的
action slogan:
一 個 活 動 的 名 號 叫 作
“Beat the bed sheet, clean the kitchen”
﹁ 打 棉 被 ， 探 灶 腳 」( 台 語 ﹚
He hoped that the campaign
就 是 希 望 藉 著 這 樣 的 一 個 活 動
would make the local people,
讓 這 個 台 灣 的 人 民
clean up and sanitize
把 你 的 居 家 生 活
their household.
弄 得 比 較 乾 淨 跟 衛 生
Every month,
好 而 且 他 每 個 月
he would find a day to talk with everyone
托 一 天 大 家 來 談
and promote his campaign.
就 來 做 這 樣 的 一 個 活 動
As a result, since then,
所 以 從 那 個 時 候 開 始
“cleaning” was referred to as pa pia (working hard).
就 把 它 簡 稱 打 披 打 拭
Before that, the locals would ask one another:
那 以 前 台 灣 人 說
Have you eaten?
你 吃 飽 沒
Later, it was changed to:
後 來 就 改 變 成 說
Did you pa pia?
你 有 打 拘 囑
After the campaign,
到 那 一 天 的 時 候
Yes, yes, I have.
有 啊 有 啊 我 有 打 拷
So the phrase pa pia caught on,
那 就 打 拘 打 拘 後 來 延 用
and evolved to its more common meaning today.
那 就 發 展 成 比 較 通 俗 的 其 他 意 涵
This is one explanation of the origin of pa pia now.
這 是 其 中 目 前 的 一 個 說 法
Events in Taiwan have always
台 灣 的 一 些 浮 現
been related to world developments.
一 直 都 跟 世 界 的 演 變 有 關 係
I feel that the people here should be more modest,
我 覺 得 台 灣 人 應 該 更 謙 卑
and should see Taiwan through the world's history.
而 且 應 該 從 世 界 史 來 看 台 灣
For instance, the 17th century
比 方 說 在 十 七 世 紀
and the 19th century were
十 九 世 紀
critical periods that shaped destiny.
這 二 個 困 緣 際 會 的 時 機
How did Taiwan gain prominence in sea navigation?
台 灣 怎 慶 浮 出 海 面
Because it was the era of great sea navigations.
困 為 大 航 海 時 代
Because of the East Asian trade.
因 為 有 東 亞 貿 易
Taiwan was located in a trade hub;
位 在 貿 易 的 交 叉 點 上
its significance thus became apparent.
所 以 台 灣 地 位 的 重 要 性 就 被 突 顯
I think it is more objective to view the history of
我 認 為 從 這 樣 的 世 界 史
Taiwan from the perspective of world history.
來 看 台 灣 史 才 是 比 較 客 觀 性 的
There are disputes
大 家 對 於 不 同 的
regarding the different versions
台 灣 的 歷 史 的 史 觀
of Taiwan's history.
其 實 有 一 些 不 同 的 爭 執
These disputes would make us wonder
這 些 爭 執 號 會 讓 我 們 覺 得 說
whether we could
我 們 可 不 可 以 用
keep history as it is,
比 較 還 歷 史 就 是 墩 史
uphold the truth as it is.
還 事 實 就 是 事 實 的 角 度
We used this perspective
用 這 樣 的 一 個 角 度
to produce a documentary
來 製 作 一 部 可 以 比 較 讓 大 家
that is more acceptable to everyone.
可 以 接 受 的 台 灣 影 像 的 歷 史 的 節 目
With this documentary,
透 過 這 個 讓 生 活 在 台 灣 的 人
people from all walks of life in Taiwan
各 種 生 活 在 台 灣 的 人
will get to understand
會 去 認 識 了 台 灣
and identify with Taiwan.
也 認 同 台 灣
This is our objective.
這 是 我 們 希 望 這 樣 的 一 個 目 標
The documentary is not only
我 們 這 一 部 紀 錄 片
for the intellectuals.
絕 對 不 是 只 做 給 知 識 份 子 看 的
The documentary is for the general public.
是 要 做 給 大 眾 看 的
It is based on meticulous research.
但 是 它 是 以 專 業 的 研 究 作 為 基 磅
We have carefully chosen the film's title.
所 以 我 們 一 開 始 就 正 名
What name did we use?
正 名 什 麼
We used the title Taiwan — A People's History.
就 是 台 灣 人 民 的 歷 史
The documentary is a history of the people,
是 人 民 的 歷 史
not the history of the rulers.
不 是 統 治 者 的 歷 史
Today, PTS
今 天 公 共 電 視
has gathered everyone to film the documentary.
集 合 大 家 一 起 來 做 這 件 事 情
It is not our intention
絕 對 不 是 要 用 那 種
to whitewash history,
美 化 歷 史 的 方 法
to create falsehood.
去 建 立 台 灣 人 民 的 虧 假
Rather, we intend to present the truth,
而 是 經 由 很 深 入 的 真 相 的
to discover our self identity.
一 種 呈 現 去 找 到 自 我
I believe that history can be viewed from several aspects.
我 覺 得 歷 史 絕 對 有 觀 點 的 問 題
It is impossible not to have perspectives.
不 可 脊 沒 有 觀 點 的 問 題
Try to factor in
盡 量 在 這 個 敏 感 的 問 題 裡 面
the different perspectives
盡 量 能 夠 在 兩 造
in sensitive issues.
或 者 多 造 的 立 場 都 要 照 顧 到
At least, the perspectives must be presented.
起 碼 都 要 介 紹 到
Only by presenting the perspectives
這 個 磐 定 清 楚
can history be interpreted.
才 能 進 入 歷 史 的 解 釋
The collection of historical materials,
包 括 歷 史 的 選 材
their choices,
取 捨 的 話
all involve different perspectives.
我 想 一 定 是 有 史 觀 的
This is inevitable.
這 個 是 免 不 了
Historical truth is very important.
那 史 實 很 重 要
The presentation of history,
所 以 在 史 實 裡 面
regardless of the perspective used,
也 就 是 在 史 觀 裡 面
should be based on facts.
必 須 有 一 些 史 實 做 基 礎
You want to be able to piece together
困 為 你 要 把 這 時 候
fragments of history that will
所 有 的 歷 史 要 拼 湊 出 一 個
be truthful yet interesting to the viewers.
能 夠 既 符 合 事 實 又 符 合 看 得 有 趣
History has to be interesting
歷 史 看 得 有 趣
and not biased.
又 不 脊 有 所 偏 頗
Therefore, editing becomes
所 以 在 所 有 的 葵 接 結 構 上 面
very important.
變 得 很 重 要
Story telling becomes very important.
說 故 事 的 方 法 變 得 很 重 要
It is not simply storytelling.
也 不 是 說 故 事
How the history is narrated becomes very important.
敏 連 歷 史 的 方 法 變 得 很 重 要
During filming,
我 在 拍 攝 的 時 候
I had my own perspective.
一 樑 會 處 理 到 我 的 角 度 是 什 麼
I did.
一 樣 會 啦
Filming and writing
影 像 的 創 作 跟 文 字 的 創 作
are different.
還 是 不 同 嘉
During filming, of course,
這 拍 出 來 的 時 候
there were many ideas
當 然 會 有 很 多 的 想 法
or arguments, and everybody disagreed.
或 說 法 大 家 不 同 意
Disagreement was not an issue.
那 不 同 意 ， 沒 關 係 嘉
We could not care too much about the consequences,
我 們 不 能 說 這 樣 的 未 來 可 能
nor could we film with apprehensions in mind.
怎 麼 樣 的 顧 慮 下 來 拍 這 個 紀 錄 片
Otherwise,
我 覺 得 這 樣 的 話
we could not continue.
我 們 都 不 要 拍 了 唰
Although the filming process
個 遇 程 會 是 一 個 為 速
was a process of serious debate,
很 嚴 重 的 辯 論
I felt it was worthwhile.
但 是 我 覺 得 我 們 值 得 這 樣 做
Because only in this way
困 為 也 唯 有 這 樣 做
could we produce
我 們 才 脊 拍 出 一 個
a distinctive documentary.
不 一 樣 的 東 西 來
Because,
困 為 這 個 東 西
after we
你 總 不 脊 說 是
spent so much money
我 們 花 了 這 麼 多 錢
and so much time on the documentary.
又 花 了 這 麼 多 時 間
If the viewers say:
大 眾 看 了 之 後 覺 得
What is this?
搭 什 麼
So dull and boring.
枯 燥 乏 味 嘉
This is unacceptable.
這 個 不 可 以
So, it is important not to stress historical viewpoints,
那 如 何 再 把 歷 史 觀 點 降 到 最 低
but to make history understandable
把 歷 史 還 原 到 一 個 可 理 解 的
and interesting.
甚 至 有 趣 的
It should be able to attract viewers' attention.
喧 引 人 家 注 意
I think this is the most important task
是 我 鷹 得 在 我 剪 接 裡 面
of editing.
很 重 要 的 任 務
I admire our director very much.
我 也 很 佩 服 導 演
Our script
可 以 將 我 們 腳 本
and our research
或 者 說 我 們 的 研 究
contained very long explanations.
講 得 冗 長 的
If it were me, it would take
我 說 遇 如 果 是 我 要 說
me more than a year to finish narrating all the events.
我 說 一 年 也 說 不 完
But our director only used
可 以 用 四 十 分 鐘
40 or 50 minutes to present the ideas.
五 十 分 鐘 來 表 達 出 來
It is really difficult
所 以 你 真 的 是 很 難
to tell so many stories within 50 minutes.
在 五 十 分 鐘 講 太 多 故 事
The history of Taiwan over the past hundreds of years,
困 為 台 灣 這 幾 百 年 來
has been one of colonization.
就 是 說 是 個 殖 民 史 啊
Wars in Taiwan
然 後 她 的 戰 火
were unending.
一 直 不 斷 的 在 台 灣 發 生
It's too bad
那 要 在 這 廖 短 的 篇 幅
that so many stories had to be squeezed
講 那 廖 多 的 故 事
into a short documentary.
我 覺 得 很 可 惜
Each story could very well
其 實 每 一 個 段 落
be developed into a good epic film,
都 可 以 發 展 很 好 的 epic film
an epic movie.
就 是 一 個 史 詩 影
One can only imagine
我 覺 得 歷 史 的 想 像 是
the events that transpired in history.
超 過 於 事 實 與 否
I wanted to
我 也 希 望 把 這 些
recreate the events
屬 於 歷 史 的 東 西
for the viewers to see,
給 觀 眾 看 到 的 是
to understand history.
一 個 歷 史 的 想 像 的 部 份
I wanted to recreate
那 要 完 全 用 那 個
the historical events.
模 擬 再 現 的 一 個 方 式
I wanted to use dramatization
也 就 是 說 劇 情 片 的 方 式
in my documentary.
來 昂 現 紀 錄 片
Characters portrayed in the documentary
它 是 直 接 從 歷 史 中
were drawn directly from history.
去 找 出 歷 史 人 物 來
The characters narrated their
自 己 來 現 身 說 法
stories as they happened.
來 說 他 們 那 個 時 候 的 故 事
Stories and events about human nature
冀 實 的 感 動 是
are often touching.
人 性 的 東 西 才 感 動
Human nature.
人 性
During the 228 Incident,
包 括 二 二 八 事 件 發 生 的 時 候
there were stories of locals,
很 多 外 省 人 被 所 謂 的 本 省 人
such as the Fulao or Hakka,
就 是 福 佬 人 或 是 客 家 人
or even the indigenous people harboring mainlanders.
甚 至 原 住 民 藏 起 來 的 故 事
There were also many locals
然 後 也 有 很 多 本 省 人
who were arrested.
他 可 脊 會 被 抓
However, there were one or two,
可 是 有 一 兩 個
a few mainlander officials
有 一 些 外 省 的 公 務 員
who risked their life to hide the locals.
冒 自 己 的 生 命 危 險 去 藏 了 本 省 人
You could not tell stories like this.
類 似 這 樣 的 故 事 你 沒 辦 法 講
Not because you're unwilling,
不 是 你 不 願 意 講
but because you didn't have enough time.
是 你 沒 有 那 個 篇 幅
I feel somewhat regretful
沒 有 那 個 篇 幅
that the documentary is not long enough
這 是 我 覺 得 拍 人 民 的 歷 史
to present the people's entire history.
這 部 分 有 點 缺 憾 啡
For instance, Dr. Mackay.
那 謹 如 說 馬 偕
Dr. Mackay
我 看 到 的 馬 偕 對 我 來 講
was very different.
他 絕 對 不 一 樣 的 是
From his diary, you would notice
你 會 發 現 從 他 的 日 記 裡 面
that he was a missionary
他 是 有 很 強 大 的 意 志 力 的
with a strong will.
一 個 傳 教 士
When he arrived in Taiwan,
他 進 來 台 灣 的 時 候
he had to teach the essence of religion.
他 發 現 他 要 傳 遇 教 義
While he preached,
他 的 傳 道 的 時 候
he also learned the language.
他 開 始 學 語 文
He was very motivated,
我 覺 得 這 個 動 力 對 我 來 講
which, for me, was impressive.
它 是 非 常 漂 亮 的
He was unlike other missionaries.
非 常 不 一 樣 的 情 操 是 跟 傳 道 士
Dr. Mackay was unique.
固 偕 之 所 以 為 馬 偕 是
Because
困 為 魂
his motivation, I believe,
那 個 動 力 讓 我 覺 得 他 開 始
made him exceedingly Chinese.
極 度 的 漢 化
He and his retinue ate from big rice pots.
他 跟 他 的 隔 從 吃 大 鍋 飯 等 等
This is the historical image that I want
這 樣 的 影 像 在 歷 史 裡 面
to capture in my film.
是 我 想 捕 抓 到 的
Another example is Yu Yung-he.
議 如 說 像 郁 永 河 這 個 角 色
You can film how
伸 可 ﹚ 江 去 把 排 險 宮 ﹣
19th Century explorers
十 九 世 紀 的 探 險 家
discovered Taiwan
他 怎 樣 發 現 台 灣
during that time.
在 那 個 時 候 的 台 灣
Yu Yung-he viewed himself
而 且 他 以 他 一 個
as a civilized person
自 以 為 的 文 明 者
who had invaded an uncivilized world.
妝 像 入 侵 到 讚 荒 世 界
As he moved closer to
那 他 愍 來 愈 走 到
the end of his journey in Taiwan,
台 灣 旅 程 的 末 後
he felt more and more ashamed.
他 愚 來 愚 自 形 慚 愧
His so-called being civilized was actually the opposite.
他 所 謂 文 明 跟 野 蠻 其 實 是 對 調 的
I thought that part was amusing.
那 一 塊 我 號 覺 得 非 常 有 趣
Because I had the facts needed to tell the story,
困 為 有 發 揮 空 間
during filming
我 到 拍 攝 現 場 的 時 候
I was more concerned about the characters.
我 比 較 關 心 的 是 人 物 角 色 的 問 題
We mentioned Yu Yung-he.
剛 才 我 們 談 郁 永 河
To my mind,
郁 永 沼 在 我 腦 子 裡 面
I didn't have to dwell too much on his story.
本 來 他 並 不 是 很 大 篇 幅 的
Yet he attracted me.
可 是 對 我 來 講
Yu was a scholar,
他 一 直 吸 引 我 的 是 一 個 秀 才
a typical Chinese scholar
一 個 典 型 的 漢 人 的 秀 才
with a unique character.
卻 有 著 不 一 樣 的 性 格
He had the character of an explorer.
他 有 著 冒 險 家 的 性 格
He arrived in Taiwan when he was over 60 years old,
公 十 幾 歲 跑 來 台 灣
and traveled from south to north in more than 10 days.
然 後 十 幾 天 從 南 到 北
His willpower and enthusiasm
他 那 種 毅 力 跟 好 奇 心
attracted me.
對 我 來 講 比 什 麼 都 重 要
To produce the history of the people of Taiwan,
要 製 作 這 樣 台 灣 人 民 的 歷 史
to reconstruct such huge events in history,
這 樣 的 大 型 的 歷 史 重 建 節 目
there were indeed so many challenges.
的 確 是 面 對 非 常 多 的 挑 戰
I was impressed
我 覺 得 比 較 印 眠 深 刻
by our production team.
就 是 我 們 這 個 製 作 團 隊
It is very difficulty to find
是 非 常 困 難 能 夠 找 到
a suitable team with cooperative members.
一 個 合 適 的 團 隊 大 家 來 配 合 的
I recall that during the process,
那 回 溯 這 個 過 程 當 中
there were at least two major
印 象 中 至 少 有 兩 次
reorganizations in the team of scriptwriters and directors
大 的 編 導 團 隊 的 改 組
due to budget constraints.
困 為 預 算 很 有 限
We spent NT$5 million per episode
坦 白 說 ， 以 一 集 五 百 萬
to reconstruct the historical events.
要 做 整 個 歷 史 重 建
Except for Episode 2
然 後 每 一 集 除 了 第 二 集
which took place during the 17th Century,
完 全 是 其 中 在
all other episodes
十 七 世 紀 大 航 海 時 代
involved huge chronological leaps.
每 一 集 時 空 跳 躍 都 是 大 跳 躁
Despite limited length of the episodes,
在 這 麼 有 限 的 篇 幅 長 度
there were so many reconstructions
然 後 還 要 重 建 這 麼 多
of props and costumes
不 同 歷 史 進 程 的
belonging to different historical periods.
一 個 美 術 道 具 服 裝 重 演
In other words,
等 於 說
faced with the decline of the
在 台 灣 面 臨 這 廖 大 的 一 個 電 影
movie and television markets in Taiwan,
跟 電 視 的 市 場 凋 萎 這 個 環 境 之 下
I must compress tasks that
我 可 脊 必 須 在 電 影 一 個 工 業
could only be accomplished by the movie industry
才 脊 完 成 的 東 西
into one that our production team
全 部 壓 縮 在 一 個 製 作 團 隊
could accomplish.
請 他 們 去 把 它 完 成 起 來
It was a big challenge.
那 是 一 個 極 大 的 挑 戰
Did Taiwan have any team capable of
那 台 灣 有 沒 有 團 隊 有 這 樣 的 能 力
reconstructing the events of history?
去 重 建 這 一 塊
It was a very difficult task.
那 是 非 常 非 常 困 難 的 事 情
I felt it was very difficult,
我 覺 得 那 是 非 常 困 難 的 事 情
but we were willing to try.
可 是 我 們 卻 類 意 嘗 試
I feel it was my personality.
我 覺 得 對 我 來 講 是 我 性 格 吧
The more impossible it was,
我 認 為 越 不 可 能
the more I wanted to do it.
我 越 會 想 做
In Taiwan television, the production of
台 灣 電 視 台 這 算 是 一 個 創 舉
this documentary is a pioneering endeavor.
要 製 作 這 樣 的 節 目
There were bigger challenges than producing it abroad.
就 要 比 國 外 面 臨 更 大 的 挑 戰
First, there was a lack of experience.
首 先 ， 第 一 個 ， 經 驗 不 足
The documentary is the first
這 是 我 們 第 一 次 電 視 史 上
history program in Taiwan television the history.
所 謂 的 ﹁ 通 史 型 」 的 節 目
This documentary attempted to reconstruct history.
歷 史 重 建 的 節 目
It was unprecedented.
硍 岡
Second, budget was limited.
第 二 個 ， 預 算 有 限
Canadian televisions are able
困 為 加 拿 大 電 視 台
to produce 30-hour documentaries
它 可 以 做 出 三 十 個 小 時
because their budget
那 他 們 的 預 算
is not only 30 times ours,
不 只 是 我 們 的 三 十 倍
it's probably 300 times more.
惡 怕 是 三 百 倍 的 預 算
Budget constraints,
那 我 們 在 這 麼 有 限 的 預 算
lack of experience, and
又 在 經 驗 不 足
limited historical materials
還 要 在 史 料 也 很 有 限 的 狀 況
were the three limitations we faced.
三 種 狀 況 重 重 限 制 下
So, to produce such a documentary
所 以 其 實 台 灣
in Taiwan
要 來 做 這 樣 的 電 視 節 目
is more challenging than doing so abroad.
要 面 臨 的 挑 戰 要 比 國 外 更 大
There were so much difficulties,
囤 難 喔 其 實 非 常 的 多 啡
much, much more.
那 個 真 的 是 困 難 重 重
I believe one
那 我 覺 得 那 個
of the extreme difficulties
其 實 一 個 很 大 的 困 難
was in finding filming locations.
是 我 覺 得 找 景
We knew
困 為 我 們 知 道
that the topography in Taiwan changes very quickly,
台 灣 的 地 貌 變 化 非 常 非 常 的 快
and we wanted to be creative.
我 們 不 斷 的 在 求 新 求 變 這 樣 子
Filming historical events on location
那 所 以 對 於 說 要 拍 歷 史 劇 那 個 景
was extremely difficult.
是 非 常 非 常 的 困 難 這 樣 子
The script had been reviewed by many,
其 實 這 個 劇 本 整 個 經 過 很 多 人
and many historians
很 多 歷 史 專 家 抽 絲 剝 薔
contributed to the framework of the stories.
整 理 架 構 起 來 一 個 故 事
The preparatory work mainly consisted of
那 對 我 來 講 你 說 前 面 的 準 備 工 作
reconstructing historical events.
對 我 來 講 就 是 如 何 重 建
The work of the director,
對 我 來 講 那 時 候 導 演 的 工 作
of the artists,
甚 至 美 術 的 工 作
and of the entire production staff
甚 至 整 個 製 作 的 工 作
focused on the reconstruction process.
是 如 何 重 建 的 過 程
To me, reconstruction
重 建 對 我 來 講 是
was the most important.
事 先 比 什 麼 都 重 要
Yet reconstruction was difficult
可 是 你 知 道 那 是 很 難 的
because Taiwan is so small.
困 為 台 灣 地 方 那 廖 小
People and topography have changed.
所 以 人 ， 地 形 地 貌 都 變 了
To reconstruct events, we had to
所 以 重 建 的 事 情 是 我 們 必 須
spend more efforts in filming
花 很 多 精 神 在 拍 的
and managing things.
在 處 理 的 事 情
That is not how he spoke.
不 是 他 講 話 的 感 覺
You cannot gesture too much.
- 駝 逛 工 樓 比 j 4 腳 宁 玫
How missionaries talk.
神 職 人 員 的 講 話
In fact,
那 事 實 上
even anthropologists or historians
我 們 的 人 類 學 家 或 歷 史 學 者
could not tell us
也 沒 有 辦 法 告 訴 我 們
whether what we were doing was correct
我 們 所 做 出 來 的 正 不 正 確
because they themselves did not have
困 為 他 們 自 己 也 沒 有
reference pictures.
這 種 圖 像 的 依 據
So, this task of
所 以 這 個 部 分 大 概 是
reconstructing historical events
這 一 次 做 這 個 歷 史 重 建
was the biggest challenge we encountered.
其 實 我 們 碰 到 的 最 大 的 挑 戰
In the early stage,
早 期 階 段
we sent people to the mainland,
其 實 我 們 有 派 人 到 大 陸
to the Fuzhou set
包 括 福 州 片 場
to look for information on costumes and props.
去 找 一 些 服 裝 道 具 的 一 些 資 料
We even looked for locations in Southern Fukien.
甚 至 到 整 個 到 闔 南 去 勘 晶
It was an arduous road.
都 走 過 這 段 很 長 的 路
The original plan was
所 以 原 來 規 劃 希 望 是
to bring the entire team
可 以 把 整 個 團 隊
to the mainland to film on location.
拉 到 大 陸 去 拍 、 取 景
This was because the people
因 為 他 們 在
along the coastal region
以 大 陸 在 邊 緣 海 岸 線 那 邊
in Southern Fukien had devoted
闇 南 那 邊 對 於 像 是 建 築 唳
more efforts to maintain buildings and topography
地 貌 的 保 留 遠 比 台 灣
compared to Taiwan.
付 出 更 多 的 心 血 的
In the selection of actors,
甚 至 包 括 演 員 管 理 選 角
it was also possible for us to find actors who looked
我 們 都 有 可 能 找 到 類 似
similar to people during the 17th and 19th centuries.
旱 期 十 七 十 九 世 紀 的 當 時 的 甚 相
Actors who are dark, thin, and tough-looking
甘 得 很 瘦 黑 精 幹 那 樣 的 人
are very difficult
那 樣 的 人 在 台 灣
to find in Taiwan nowadays.
已 經 是 非 常 非 常 難 找 到 了
No. 11 is Shih Lang, correct?
11 號 是 施 琅 對 不 對
Shih Lang's arrival in Taiwan?
施 琅 進 台 灣 嗲
12? We are shooting 12 scenes today.
12 嗎 今 天 要 拍 12 個 鏡 位
You guys,
﹣ 苦 ﹤ 年 1 大 羯 42 第 莘
you will appear in the 8 o'clock slot.
作 引 1 姬 ﹣ 戈 吒 # 志 八 ﹍ 黑 y 篇 j
You want me to faint?
伸 要 ﹣ 我 雷 侯 | ” 呣
Why is he standing there?
他 怎 麼 一 直 在 旁 邊
Strange.
奇 怪 啊
I think Taiwan does not have
我 覺 得 台 灣 沒 有 條 件
what it takes to film a history series.
拍 歷 史 劇 的 東 西
First, the movie industry here is almost non-existent.
第 一 個 台 灣 的 電 影 工 業 幾 乎 沒 有
It is thus difficult to make history films.
拍 歷 史 談 何 容 易 啊
For costumes and art design,
從 衣 服 ， 從 美 術 的 人 才 這 些 東 西
I feel our team is...,
我 覺 得 我 們 的 團 隊
to quote program manager Wang Ya-wei,
以 套 一 個 王 亞 維 的 意 思
it is extreme difficult
以 一 家 的 公 司
for one company
做 整 個 電 影 工 業 的 事 情
to do the work of an entire movie industry.
那 是 非 常 非 常 困 難 的 事 情
I believe that these issues
那 可 是 這 些 東 西
can be resolved with money.
我 覺 得 只 要 有 錢 就 可 以 克 服 的
There are also issues that money cannot resolve,
可 是 有 些 東 西 有 錢 也 克 服 不 了 的
such as the topography.
我 覺 得 地 形 地 貌 的 問 題
We wanted to film Keelung Harbor and Tamsui.
好 比 說 我 們 拍 基 隆 港 ， 拍 淡 水
It was impossible
那 幾 乎 無 法 取 鏡 了
to find a location
你 幾 乎 找 不 到 一 個
that was similar
當 年 那 個 原 貌
to earlier times.
是 怎 麼 樣 的 一 個 東 西
You couldn't even find places that were similar.
甚 至 你 也 無 法 找 到 比 較 接 近 的
Taiwan is this small.
小 阱 這 麼 台 灣 就 這
I was filming Cheng Cheng-kung
比 如 說 我 們 拍 鄭 成 功
in Kunni in Tainan.
臺 南 鯤 鰱 那 個 地 方
The Kunni of today
現 在 的 鯤 鯓
no longer resembles the Kunni of the past.
已 經 看 不 出 當 年 的 情 境 了
Instead, we found some place similar
反 而 我 們 在 北 部 發 現
in northern Taiwan.
比 較 接 近 的 那 個 地 形 地 貌
But still the similarities were limited.
可 是 那 個 角 度 是 非 常 有 限 的
We could only shoot at certain angles;
角 度 也 只 不 過 是 一 個 方 向 的 角 度
otherwise, viewers would notice.
住 一 3 暴 孕 兄 閤 ﹣ 烙 一 空 菱 了
The difficulty
困 難 的 都 是
lies in the setting.
主 要 是 是 景 啦
The setting was the most serious problem.
場 景 我 覺 得 是 最 嚴 重 的 問 題
Even if the budget was okay,
你 即 便 聽 起 來 預 算 還 OK
when you really started to build the sets,
但 是 你 真 的 要 去 做 那 些 場 景
you couldn't do it even with the budget.
余 有 錢 乩 ﹒ 碣 ﹣ 不 ﹤ 出 仁 ﹣
The environment had changed.
已 經 沒 有 那 個 環 境
Only a few places are suitable for filming.
已 經 沒 有 ， 很 少 了
No matter how you shoot, there are too many buildings.
怎 麼 拍 都 有 很 多 大 樓 啊
Unless you have a system like that of Hollywood.
除 非 你 真 的 像 好 萊 塢 那 個 系 統
You can build a large set,
到 一 個 大 片 場 整 個 蓋 起 來
a Japanese street or an entire village.
一 條 日 本 的 街 道 ， 一 個 村 落
Only with that can you be able to film
那 才 脊 夠 真 正 拍 到 那 種
locations that reflect the times.
我 覺 得 最 美 的 時 代 感 的 東 西
Things that truly reflect their times are difficult to find.
最 詳 實 的 時 代 惹 的 東 西 都 很 難
Often times, you borrow a piece here,
大 部 分 都 是 這 樣 借 一 塊
a piece there.
那 借 一 塊
You angle your camera a little bit here,
這 邊 避 一 點
a little bit there.
那 邊 避 一 點
The periods we were filming didn't have photography.
我 們 拍 的 時 候 連 照 相 術 都 沒 有
We had to rely on limited historical information.
靠 著 有 限 歷 史 資 料 去 重 建
Without photographs,
畫 像 都 沒 有
it was difficult.
是 相 當 困 難 的
I believe
我 覺 得 最 大 困 難 你 不 問 我
the most difficult was,
我 覺 得 最 大 困 難 是
apart from changes in topography,
除 了 地 形 地 貌 轉 換 之 外
that people had also changed.
我 們 的 人 種 也 變 了
While I was filming,
那 事 實 上 我 拍 的 時 候
I wanted to shoot faces.
我 最 想 拍 的 是 人 的 臉 型
I had intended to shoot the change in the facial features
本 來 我 企 圖 是 拍 不 同 的 漢 人
of the different Han immigrants.
移 民 社 會 的 臉 塊 的 變 化
To me, it was most interesting
對 我 來 講 是 最 有 趣 的
because after the Han arrived in Taiwan,
困 為 我 覺 得 漢 人 來 台 灣 之 後
they underwent many assimilations with others.
經 遇 好 幾 次 的 各 民 族 的 融 合
To me, the images
所 以 對 我 來 講
of the people of Taiwan
台 灣 人 的 形 象
attracted me more than anything else.
吸 引 我 超 過 於 任 何 事 情
But it was difficult for me to capture these on film.
可 是 我 很 難 拍 到 這 些 東 西
The peoples have changed.
因 為 人 種 已 經 變 變 到 現 在
They are different from what I expected.
跟 我 原 來 想 法 不 太 一 樣
Second is the reconstruction process.
第 二 個 就 是 重 建 的 遇 程
These actors have grown fat.
這 些 人 都 變 胖
None of them is skinny.
沒 有 一 個 瘦 瘦 的
However, there were no fat people back then.
那 個 年 代 不 可 能 有 胖 子
It's that simple.
很 簡 單
So when we were screening actors,
所 以 住 知 道 我 們 找 演 員 的 時 候
we had problems.
毒 一 個 碰 到 的 問 題
There were too many fat actors.
就 是 胖 子 太 多 太 多
With the living conditions then,
困 為 那 個 時 候 的 生 活 條 件
the people should have been skinny.
懋 該 都 非 常 瘦 才 對
No one was fat.
沒 有 胖 子
We were almost unable to find skinny actors.
那 我 們 幾 乎 找 不 到 瘦 子
Even among the indigenous people,
甚 至 我 們 在 原 住 民 裡 面
no one was skinny.
真 的 找 不 到 那 種 乾 瘦 的
The physical size of the people have changed.
人 的 體 態 形 狀 都 變 了
The director had hoped
原 本 導 演 是 希 望
that if the phrase pa pia
如 果 取 ﹁ 打 拆 」
was used as title,
這 樣 的 一 個 大 標 題 的 話
he would need a
他 可 能 需 能 需 要 一 個 比 較
famous calligrapher
知 名 的 書 法 家
or a persuasive calligrapher
或 是 比 較 有 說 服 力 的 書 法 家
to write the characters.
來 題 這 個 字
The director thought about
後 來 就 想 到 了
inviting Tang Yang-tzu to write the characters.
請 董 陽 孜 老 師 來 題 這 個 字
I thought that since
那 我 覺 得 既 然 請 到
a famous calligrapher had been invited,
這 廖 有 名 的 老 師 來 寫 了
the focus could be on the manner
所 以 我 希 望 它 的 表 現 是 重 點
in which the characters pa pia were written.
就 是 寫 這 個 ﹁ 打 拆 」
We could use
這 兩 個 字 的 筆 順
the strokes of the two characters
用 它 的 筆 順 帶 出 一 丞
to bring out images of major characters,
比 較 重 要 人 物 的 畫 面
or to bring out major events.
配 一 些 比 較 重 大 的 場 面
But how do you reconstruct the characters and events?
你 要 怎 麼 去 重 建
Many characters and events
它 很 多 東 西 都 只 是
were mere passages in history books.
書 上 面 的 一 段 文 字
What images do those passages conjure?
這 個 文 字 交 代 了 什 麼
With those passages,
那 這 個 文 字
you need to transform them into images and locations.
﹣ 來 站 人 糾 轉 畢 專 鎮 成 際 三 2 面 ﹍ 轉 專 鎮 戎 場 一 玲 寸 ﹍ 仁
If you merely concentrated on
那 你 如 果 全 部
faithful reconstruction of the passages,
都 去 鑽 重 建 這 一 塞 的 話
I believe it would be
那 我 覺 得
less meaningful to the viewers.
對 看 的 人 來 說 意 義 不 大
Instead, I believe in
我 覺 得 反 而 是
providing some latitude,
給 他 們 一 點 想 像 的 空 間
because history
困 為 我 覺 得 歷 史
is actually very romantic.
這 種 東 西 其 實 是 很 浪 漫 的
It's not to say that I did not follow historical facts,
不 要 說 完 全 不 按 照 那 個
nor did I present the facts in an abstract level.
我 只 是 覺 得 也 不 到 抽 象 的 程 度
I believe I conveyed the message.
至 少 說 我 覺 得 是 寫 意 的
Not the every factual detail, but I did convey the message.
不 是 寫 實 ， 是 寫 意 的
We conveyed the message
我 們 把 那 個 意 思 帶 到
and provide the viewers some latitude.
然 後 空 間 是 留 給 看 的 人
I believe that was more important.
我 覺 得 那 東 西 比 較 重 要
For instance,
就 好 像 我 們 去 做 那 個
we built a set duplicating
那 時 候 是 熟 蘭 遮 城 的 室 內
the inside of Fort Zeelandia.
室 內 的 場 景
We did not actually follow the design plan.
我 們 並 沒 有 完 全 照 著 圖 面 去 做
I thought of using lights and shadows
我 覺 得 那 個 東 西 我 們 用 光 影
and imagination
然 後 用 很 多 的 想 像 力 的 東 西
to build the set.
去 把 它 作 出 來
I believe the set had the right feel.
我 覺 得 那 感 覺 是 對 的
When the viewers
那 東 西 在 觀 真
see it, they would naturally
他 看 到 的 時 候
feel that it is right although we did not tell
他 自 然 就 會 感 覺 對 了
the viewers that the feeling was right.
但 是 我 們 沒 有 刻 意 去 跟 他 說
It is like that.
就 是 這 個 樣 子
If we told the actors
他 們 姜 果 是
what were the emotions
我 們 告 訴 他
of the farewell scene
他 們 的 訣 別 的 氣 氟 是 怎 麼 樣 子
we could replicate and capture the feelings and emotions.
我 覺 得 我 們 抓 的 是 氣 氛 跟 感 覺
You need to simulate the situation.
﹣ 菲 ﹤ ﹣ 婚 ﹣ 稚 拈 苑 ‧ 蓑 # 夷 曰 2 切 天 為 埴
Of course, you have to use your imagination.
當 煌 你 就 要 壹 量 想 健
If the simulated atmosphere was right,
想 像 假 如 出 來 的 氣 氛 對 了
the emotions would be right.
大 概 號 對 了
Of course, it was more difficult
當 然 比 較 辛 苺 啦
when we had to show details of the props.
就 是 裡 面 要 key 的 東 西
The props would have to be built in more detail.
他 要 做 的 工 要 做 比 較 細
The more detail, the better the effects.
比 較 細 出 來 的 效 果 比 較 好
If you could shoot on location,
那 當 然 假 如 你 能 在 外 景 拍
it would be the best.
那 當 然 外 景 就 是 最 好 的
Because the set would become more realistic.
比 較 接 近 當 時 狀 態
Even not filming inside the studio
完 全 沒 有 進 棚
the set was easily controlled,
片 場 還 是 好 控 制
but we needed extra efforts.
但 是 就 要 花 一 點 功 夫
I was most excited
我 覺 得 最 興 奮 的
shooting the ship scene.
當 然 就 是 去 搭 去 做 船 的 那 一 塊 吧
I remember one time
我 記 得 有 一 次 就 是
filming the second episode on location.
當 我 們 到 第 二 集 的 拍 攝 現 場
It was the sea battle between Cheng Cheng-kung and the Dutch,
拍 鄭 荷 海 戰
which was the 916 Sea Battle.
就 是 九 一 六 台 3 是 九 一 六 台 江 外 海 之 戰
When we were filming,
那 場 戲 的 時 候
we invited Weng Chia-yin,
我 們 請 了 翁 佳 音 老 師
who was the advisor for Episode 2,
就 是 第 二 雅 的 指 導 委 員
to the set.
到 片 場 去 的 時 候
I could see
我 可 以 看 到 他 的 那 個 表 情
excitement
那 是 好 像 我 看 到 他 的 高 興
written all over his face.
就 是 寫 在 他 臉 上
Weng had visited the Netherlands before,
困 為 他 之 前 去 過 荷 蘭 實 地 採 芝 遇
and he knew that the Dutch
他 也 知 道 那 邊
had built
也 重 建 了 一 艘 十 七 世 紀
a 17th century battleship
大 航 海 時 代 的 海 洋 國 的
of the great sea navigation era.
那 個 戰 艦 在 那 邊
So, when he saw
所 以 當 他 看 到 我 們
the ship we had built
把 那 個 船 艙 複 製 在
at the Pali set,
八 里 片 場 的 時 候
he was so excited.
我 看 到 他 的 那 個 興 奮
Weng was a scholar.
就 一 個 學 者 來 講
His research paper
他 的 paperwork 研 究 報 告
has been read, digested,
被 閱 讀 了 ， 被 消 化 了
and transformed into film.
然 後 被 改 變 成 影 像 的 時 候
Excitement
那 個 喜 悅 完 全 在 他 臉 上
was on his face.
可 以 讀 到
The reproduction was
所 以 那 個 重 建 度 真 的
more than 90 percent accurate.
高 達 百 分 之 九 十 以 上
He said even the canons looked authentic.
他 說 連 大 砲 都 幾 可 亂 真 啊
I myself was also happy.
所 以 這 點 我 還 蠻 開 心 的
We chatted
像 我 們 聊 一 聊
with the director.
跟 導 演 聊 一 聊
We had given the director some limitations.
之 前 我 們 給 了 他 那 個 限 制
Then you would feel very confident
你 諮 X 2 一 紙 2 大
because you wouldn't let him, say,
因 為 你 也 不 能 讓 他 說
he wanted to shoot a sea battle
他 今 天 想 要 拍 一 個 海 戰
and he'll go all out
就 用 了 完 完 全 全
filming bloody battles in the raging sea.
就 是 那 種 怖 海 爭 鋒 的 拍 法
So then would you do it?
那 你 怎 麼 玩
We did not, for example,
我 們 沒 有 比 姐 說
actually put a ship
把 它 放 在 大 海 裡 面
at sea,
的 一 艘 船 這 樣 子
because it would be
困 為 那 個 實 在 是 太
too difficult to do.
執 行 度 太 高
It would be very difficult.
困 難 度 太 高
We were not filming the Titanic.
我 們 真 的 不 是 在 拍 鐵 達 尼 號
I believe that without
我 覺 得 住 這 些 東 西 住 把 它 放 大 了
the proper environment,
其 實 你 沒 有 那 個 環 境 其 實 你
magnifying the battle scene
你 把 它 放 大
would serve no purpose.
其 實 是 沒 有 意 義 的
Yes, you would feel more restricted.
對 啊 ， 你 反 而 會 有 更 多 的 限 制
When we were shooting Cheng Cheng-kung's ship,
就 像 我 們 在 拍 鄭 成 功 的 船 的 時 候
we did it inside the studio.
你 把 宁 放 在 棚 內
But our post-production could not keep up,
其 實 你 的 後 期 跟 不 上
and we had to find out what it was that's causing the delay.
你 要 去 拿 那 些 東 西 你 跟 不 上
For the scene inside the Dutch ship,
我 覺 得 荷 蘭 船 艙 那 一 幕 至 少 說
although there were limitations,
好 我 就 給 你 限 制
we were able to
可 是 我 在 那 個 限 制 裡 面
work around the limitations
做 得 很 完 整
and come up with a complete work.
就 把 它 做 得 很 完 整
All the details were done this way.
所 有 的 細 節 都 去 做 到 這 樣 子
I felt this was the right way,
那 這 個 東 西 我 就 覺 得 是 一 個 好 的
because you capture the exact emotions on film,
因 為 你 一 樣 可 以 拍 出 那 種 感 覺
and we could reproduce intricate details.
精 緻 度 都 可 以 做 出 來 了
Writers and historians
可 能 對 文 字 工 作 者 歷 史 學 者
can simply use words to describe an epic battle.
他 們 用 千 軍 萬 馬 四 個 字 就 解 決 了
But in film,
但 是 對 我 們 影 像 工 作 者 勢 必
we have to use the computer
要 用 很 多 電 腦 的 duplication 的
during post-production
後 期 複 製 技 術 來 完 成
to painstakingly produce
很 多 千 軍 萬 馬 或 是 大 的 海 戰
the large-scale battles at sea or on land.
大 的 陸 戰 的 那 種 陣 仗 場 面
Also,
而 且 這 部 片 子
the documentary is the first in TV history
又 是 號 稱 電 視 史 上
to use movie magic,
第 一 次 用 movie magic
so producing the documentary
所 以 其 實 台 灣 要 製 作 這 樣 的 節 目
in Taiwan is more challenging than it is abroad.
要 面 臨 的 挑 戰 要 比 國 外 要 更 大
The production process
執 行 的 話
is very complicated.
講 起 來 會 非 常 複 雜 吧
There were in total
就 是 說 它 其 實 總 共
close to a hundred
算 起 來 有 幾 乎 上 百 個
special effects
前 面 四 集 來 說 ， 總 共 上 百 個
in the first four episodes.
超 過 一 百 個 以 上 的 特 效 合 成 畫 面
Some were animations.
甚 至 是 動 畫 的 畫 面
Hours and hours were spent
所 以 說 以 做 的 時 間 來 說
on this difficult task.
根 本 就 是 非 常 的 艱 鉅 的 任 務
It was unprecedented.
也 從 來 沒 有
I believe there never was any
我 覺 得 從 來 沒 有
TV program that used the same kinds of special effects.
一 個 電 視 節 目 是 這 樣 子 做 特 效 的
In the beginning,
然 後 一 開 始
due to time constraints
可 能 是 困 為 時 間 的 關 係
and lack of experience,
也 困 為 經 驗 的 關 係
many things had yet to mesh.
我 覺 得 很 多 時 候 是 需 要 磨 合 的
We had produced many TV ads.
我 們 廣 告 片 做 很 多
So when we relied on our experience
所 以 我 們 經 驗 上 去 處 理
to process certain special effects details,
某 些 細 節 的 特 效 的 時 候
we were nitpicking.
會 比 較 吹 毛 求 疵 一 點
Yet TV documentaries do not allow you
可 是 電 視 劇 好 像 不 容 許 你
to work into details.
做 太 大 細 部 的 動 作
Thus we simply did our best
所 以 說 我 們 可 能 盡 自 己 的 努 力
or did what was possible
或 是 盡 可 能 吧
to produce something satisfactory to us.
做 到 一 些 讓 自 己 滿 意 的 東 西
Historical documentaries or
其 實 就 是 在 講 一 些 歷 史
films based on stringent research
或 是 說 比 較 有 考 據 的 紀 錄 片 的 時 候
usually cover much serious topics.
可 能 牽 涉 的 會 比 較 嚴 肅 一 點
To us
所 以 我 們 通 常 拍 起 來
or to the viewers,
或 者 是 看 起 來
these films could be boring.
感 覺 會 比 較 枯 燥
That's why the director and |
所 以 說 導 演 跟 我 的 想 法
decided to add more
可 能 會 加 入 一 些
interesting animations.
新 奇 的 動 畫 表 現 這 樣 子
Basically, I hope each episode
基 本 上 我 希 望 是 每 一 集
is unique in its own way.
它 其 實 都 有 特 別 的 味 道 吧
For instance, in the first episode,
謹 如 說 第 一 集
we focused on computer animation and
我 們 比 較 重 視 一 點 電 腦 動 畫
the realism of the evolution of the earth.
一 點 真 實 地 球 演 變 的 過 程
How did Taiwan come about?
台 灣 怎 廖 生 成 的 這 樣 子
During our 3-D production,
在 3D 製 作 的 過 程 裏 面
we first tried to obtain the desired images,
原 則 上 先 拿 到 設 定 的 畫 面 之 後
then decide how big the set would be.
再 決 定 場 景 要 做 多 大
At this point,
這 時 候 就 會 決 定
the models would be decided.
要 做 怎 樣 子 的 模 型
We then proceeded
那 當 模 壅 處 理 妝 之 後
to the texture of the models.
我 們 會 再 處 理 它 的 質 惹
We pasted pictures and
那 就 是 把 它 上 貼 圖
manipulated the coloring effects.
處 理 一 些 顏 色 的 感 覺
If the models
那 姜 果 模 型 本 身
had to be movable,
還 要 再 做 動 作 的 話
we installed frameworks
我 們 可 能 還 要 再 架 骨 架
to provide simple movements.
讓 它 調 一 些 動 作
After that,
這 整 個 做 完 之 後
we improved
我 們 會 再 做
the image quality.
讓 這 個 畫 面 質 感 變 好
Through a process called rendering.
那 個 叫 算 圖
After rendering,
算 圖 的 動 作 完 成 之 後
if we still needed smoke and fire,
如 果 我 們 還 有 一 些 煙 啡 火 啡
it would be more difficult
那 這 些 在 3D 軟 體 製 作 上
to create using 3-D software.
比 較 複 雜 的
We would use
我 們 就 可 能 用 一 些
2-D software to provide these special effects.
2D 的 合 成 軟 體 去 做 一 些 特 效
The entire procedure involved
所 以 整 個 過 程 就 是
modeling and texturing,
建 模 、 處 理 質 感
making the images move, and rendering.
讓 畫 面 動 起 來 、 算 完 圖
After rendering came integration,
那 算 完 圖 之 後 有 合 成
we might even add some more things.
也 許 我 們 再 疊 一 些 東 西 上 去
For example, this wall painting.
用 這 個 壁 畫 喔
We initially wanted
是 我 們 原 始 想 說 就 是 要 讓 它
simple lines,
看 起 來 比 較 簡 單 的 線 條
and also clearly show
然 後 很 清 楚 的
some activities of the ancient people
可 以 表 達 當 時 的 社 會
in the community during that time.
一 些 原 始 人 他 們 活 動 的 一 些 型 態
Like this,
這 樣 子
the human outline and
跟 現 在 看 到 的 人 形 跺
the animation were patterned
動 畫 的 表 現
after the wall paintings of
是 參 考 一 些 歐 洲 啊 ， 亞 洲
indigenous people in Europe and Asia.
或 是 一 些 原 住 民 的 一 些 壁 畫
It was a combination of many things.
所 有 的 東 西 融 合
We tried to imitate its style
那 我 們 再 盡 可 能 去 模 仿 它 的 風 格
to create something new.
產 生 一 個 新 的 東 西
It was just like regular graffiti.
其 實 它 很 像 一 般 的 塗 鴉
Because they engaged in these activities,
困 為 當 時 他 們 有 這 些 活 動
we imitated them.
我 們 才 去 模 仿
Or, we imagined what they did.
或 是 說 想 像 他 可 能 會 有 哪 些 的
For example, hunting
謹 姜 說 獵 捕 的 行 為
or domesticating dogs.
或 者 是 養 育 狗 啊
These activities were written in historical records.
困 為 是 史 料 上 是 有 記 載
They discovered
他 們 當 初 是 有 發 現
skeletons of dogs,
那 個 狗 的 殘 髂
so we thought there must be
所 以 我 們 才 想 說 應 該 有
dogs living with the humans.
翁 跟 人 類 一 起 生 活 的 東 西
So we had a small dog
所 以 會 有 一 隻 小 狗
running about.
在 跑 來 跑 去 這 樣 子
I used my imagination
那 其 實 是 我 發 揮 一 點 想 像 力
to make these serious
讓 這 些 比 較 矇 肅 的
and boring scenes
比 較 枯 燥 的 這 個 劇 情
a bit lively.
讓 它 活 潑 一 點
It was really
然 後 咒 ， 它 其 實 是
an integration of
一 個 2D 跟 3D 的 結 合
2D and 3D animation.
動 畫 的 結 合
The lines were drawn with 2D,
緝 條 的 部 份 是 2D 畫 的
then combined with the 3D mountains.
最 後 才 合 成 在 3D 的 山 璧 上 面
In the second episode, of the great sea navigation era,
第 二 集 比 如 像 大 航 海 的 時 候
the maps were very important.
地 圖 很 重 要
We wanted to have different types of maps
所 以 我 們 地 圖 表 現 非 常 的 多 樣
because I wanted to have different presentations.
我 希 望 有 不 同 的 表 現 方 式 啡
I wanted the indicators on the maps
跺 以 前 的 地 圖 指 標 上
to be different from previous ones.
有 一 些 不 一 樣 的 演 釋 方 式
The maps were very important,
所 以 地 圖 很 重 要
with all the countries and places.
包 括 哪 一 國 從 哪 裡 來 之 類 的
It was very complicated.
那 非 常 的 葉 雜
For example,
那 姜 果 說
if all maps looked similar,
体 每 一 徐 地 圓 都 差 丕 多
it would be boring.
我 覺 得 蠻 無 聊 的 啡
The visuals would be dull.
就 是 你 的 視 覺 上 會 蠻 乏 味 的
So I spent lots of efforts
所 以 說 我 花 了 很 多 力 氣 在
to highlight the maps
地 圖 怎 麼 表 現
yet keeping them in line with the tone.
又 不 能 讓 它 太 跳 tone
The third episode was more like opera.
第 三 集 就 有 一 點 傾 向 於 戲 曲 啊
It is livelier.
比 較 活 潑
The episode contained fight scenes using weapons,
它 本 身 就 械 門 什 麼 的
and the scenes were more repetitive.
是 比 較 重 複 性 蠻 高 的
The episode contained a more serious theme.
然 後 它 那 個 題 材 很 硬
So how do you soften it a bit,
你 怎 廖 讓 它 軟 化 一 點
and make it more digestible
讓 它 比 較 好 消 化
for the audience?
讓 觀 眾 比 較 好 消 化
I thought of making it more interesting.
我 覺 得 看 起 來 是 一 點 有 趣
When you find something interesting
有 趣 中 間 你 就 會 無 形 去 吸 收
you would unconsciously absorb what the plot is offering you.
它 的 劇 情 要 給 你 的 東 西
I liked adding ancient
其 實 我 還 蠻 喜 歡 用 一 些
materials in the film.
古 典 的 素 材 加 在 這 個 案 子 裡
That is, introducing
就 是 說 它 其 實 是
ancient materials into
就 是 說 古 典 的 元 素
some modern special effects
放 在 一 些 現 代 的 特 效
or computer animations.
或 是 電 腦 動 畫 上 面
It gave the film more of a historical persona.
它 給 我 慶 覺 比 較 有 歷 史 特 色 吧
The shadow puppet show was an interesting performance.
那 皮 影 戲 是 很 有 趣 的 一 個 戲 劇
I thought
我 覺 得 啦
it had artistic taste,
它 是 一 個 很 有 美 術 惹
design creativity,
很 有 圖 案 式 的 感 覺
even creative animation.
甚 至 是 動 畫 式 的 感 覺
Initially, I wanted to invite
那 當 當 初 其 實 是 想 要 用
a shadow puppet troupe to perform.
真 的 皮 影 戲 團 來 演
But new puppets would have to be made,
可 是 困 為 要 重 新 製 作 皮 影 戲 偶
and the script would have to be rewritten.
加 上 它 的 戲 劇 可 能 要 重 編
Also, the availability of the troupe was a concern,
加 上 那 個 戲 團 的 時 間
so was the budget.
還 有 經 費 種 種 啦
Finally we decided
最 後 可 能 我 們 想 到
that a more creative way
一 個 比 較 新 的 方 式
would be to use animation, which would be interesting.
它 可 能 有 動 畫 表 現 也 蠻 有 趣 的
I wanted it to be slightly abstract,
我 希 望 它 有 一 點 拙 瞞 式 的 意 涵
especially when I read
那 尤 其 是 我 看 到
the story of Chu Yi-kuei.
朱 一 貴 的 故 事 的 時 候
I thought it was dramatic.
我 覺 得 它 本 身 就 蠻 有 戲 劇 性 的
Breeding ducks,
養 的 鴨 子 啊
commanding ducks to form a line.
命 令 鴨 子 排 隊 啊 之 類 的
These were meant for film.
就 本 身 蠻 有 戲 的 感 覺
If this segment were
可 是 這 一 段
dramatized,
姜 果 是 戲 劇 去 拍 的 話
it would become unexciting
可 能 就 有 一 點 無 趣 吧
and difficult to film.
而 且 也 不 容 易 拍 成
Using shadow puppets might
可 是 用 皮 影 戲 表 現 的 話
make it more interesting
可 能 會 還 讚 有 趣
and lively.
還 蠻 活 潢 的 這 樣 子
It would also attract viewers.
一 方 面 也 蠻 吸 引 人 的
Because Taiwan's history
困 為 台 灣 的 歷 史 是
is dramatic.
還 蠻 具 戲 劇 性 的
Using music to express
那 怎 麼 用 音 樂 去 表 現
happiness, anger, sadness, and fun
爻 皿 2 ﹣ 唐 ﹣ 夾 2 ﹣ 袂 ﹍ 榮 &
was also a big challenge.
算 是 一 個 蠻 大 的 挑 戰 的
Since the documentary
一 剛 開 始 做 的 時 候 會 想 到
involved the history of Taiwan,
這 犖 扯 到 台 灣 的 歷 史
traditional Taiwanese music first came to mind.
所 以 有 想 到 台 灣 的 古 調
Or music from the period of Japanese occupation,
或 者 是 一 些 日 據 時 代 的 歌 曲
or something similar.
或 是 什 麼
Later, I thought I should
可 是 後 來 我 覺 得 我 懋 該 有
project my own feeling,
我 自 己 的 感 覺 來 做 出 來
because I do not want to say
而 不 是 我 不 是 希 望 說
I referred to this and that,
我 參 考 這 個 參 考 那 個
and then the music just came together.
然 後 它 就 是 這 樣 子 彈 出 來 了
You will see,
你 會 看 到
it is like looking at a clock.
愛 覺 好 像 是 看 到 時 鐘 的
The dials running in the opposite direction;
它 的 時 針 在 倒 轉 的 感 覺
it's the feeling of time passing.
就 是 那 個 時 間 流 逝 的 愁 覺
I felt the music was
我 會 覺 得 它 有 一 點
slightly melancholic,
感 傷 的 元 素 在 裡 面
yet I did not feel
可 是 我 不 全 然 鷹 得
the music was sad.
那 是 很 悲 傷 的 旋 律
In its melancholy,
我 覺 得 它 在 憎 傷 的 一 部 份
the music contained
對 我 來 講 也 有 部 份
elements of hope.
希 望 的 愛 鷹 的 元 素 在 裡 面
Just like when I was little,
很 像 是 小 時 候
I would hear a melody
聽 到 的 某 一 段 旋 律
or whatever
或 是 什 麼 之 類 的
that conjured
起 碼 會 讓 我 自 己 有 一 個
past feelings.
妝 像 是 一 個 舊 時 光 的 感 覺
In fact, I started
其 實 真 正 這 個 主 旋 律
to identify with the melody
對 我 開 始 比 較 有 共 鳴 的 時 候
when I was doing the film title.
是 在 做 片 頭 的 時 候
The music going with the film title was the first to appear.
困 為 片 頭 的 音 樂 要 先 出 來
I wanted strings
然 後 ， 一 開 始 做 號 想 要 用 弦 樂 器
because string instruments
因 為 弦 樂 器 畢 竟 對 我 來 講
can better
是 在 情 慶 的 張 力 上 面
relate feelings.
比 較 覽 源 較 豐 富 的 樂 器
I cannot forget a scene
印 象 特 別 深 刻 的 話
at the end of episode six,
可 能 是 第 公 集 後 面 的 那 個
where Taiwanese were turned into Japanese soldiers.
講 到 台 灣 人 變 日 本 兵 的 那 個 部 份
After Japan lost the war,
可 是 戰 敗 之 後
the Nationalist government, which was the former enemy,
原 本 敵 軍 的 國 民 政 府 又 要 來
arrived in Taiwan, and soldiers had identity crisis.
就 是 一 種 身 份 的 迷 惘 吧
I had strong emotions
可 能 我 做 那 一 場
while filming that segment.
比 較 有 特 別 的 感 覺
Maybe it was because
或 許 是 那 個 部 份 的 歷 史
that part of history was less distant
比 較 靠 近 自 己
and I felt connected.
所 以 比 較 有 connect 比 較 有 連 結
Maybe it was more difficult for me
可 能 太 久 遠 的 年 代 對 我 來 講
to understand the history of the long past.
可 脊 要 去 了 解 過 去
But the arrival of the Nationalist government
這 個 年 代 可 能 比 較 靠 近
was the time of my grandparents.
就 是 我 阿 公 阿 嬛 的 時 代
The accompanying music
其 實 很 簡 單 的
was actually very simple.
那 一 段 的 配 樂
It was very simple.
其 實 很 簡 單
But I believe that the simpler a music is,
可 是 通 常 我 覺 得 越 簡 單 的 東 西
the easier it can touch people.
好 像 有 時 候 特 別 容 易 慰 動 人 吧
The music
那 一 場 音 樂 就 是
was basically guitar,
我 有 把 主 旋 律
but I added flute
它 是 一 個 吉 他 的 版 本
to the melody.
配 上 笛 子 吧
The clip was U.S. warplanes strafing.
那 個 畫 面 是 美 軍 的 戰 機 在 掃 射
It was a valuable documentary film
那 懋 該 是 蠻 珍 貴 的 紀 錄 片
because it was in color.
困 為 是 彩 色 的
The shot was taken from the plane, strafing at Taiwan.
它 從 戰 機 上 面 拍 被 掃 射 的 台 灣
Yes, that segment evoked feelings.
對 啊 ， 那 一 段 蠻 有 感 覺 的
Do I sound like I'm bragging?
這 樣 講 是 不 是 很 臭 屁 啊
Inserting my own score and the film becomes touching?
困 為 配 上 自 己 的 音 樂 就 有 惹 覺
But to me,
可 是 對 我 來 講
that scene was touching.
那 場 戲 對 我 蠻 有 感 覺 的
Maybe it was the documentary film itself.
或 許 是 紀 錄 片 帶 給 我 的 感 覺
Or maybe,
就 是 或 許 因 為
since I did not experience the era,
自 己 沒 有 經 歷 過 那 個 年 代
when I saw how
特 別 會 覺 得 看 到 那 樣 子 的 畫 面
my homeland was bombed
看 到 自 己 的 土 地 是 那 樣 的 被 轟 炵
I feel
會 特 別 的 有 一 種
specially sad.
會 覺 得 難 過 吧 對 啊
But I never did experience the era,
可 是 自 己 又 沒 經 歷 過 那 個 年 代
so I could only use music
所 以 我 只 脊 夠 用 音 樂
to express that feeling.
去 描 述 那 個 感 覺